so today I want to review a book that I
think is absolutely vital for
understanding how we got into the global
predicaments that we're in and how we
can get out of them and that is this
book moral origins the evolution of
virtue altruism and shame by Christopher
Bohm so Christopher Boehm is a highly
respected anthropologist who initially
worked with Jane Goodall studying
primate behavior and then later went on
to study social behavior immorality and
hunter-gatherer societies and what he
did in this book moral origins is he
explored the question how did social
behavior arise in human evolution and in
particular during the long period of
time from roughly 200,000 years ago up
until the present in some cases or
10,000 years ago before agrarian
societies he has the question in that
context how did cooperation arise how
was antisocial behavior contained and
what can we learn about that in order to
create social policies today that help
us manage the sanctioning of bad
behavior on the promotion of good
behavior in society writ large so what
he found that I think is extremely
helpful for us is he found that there is
always a small percentage of any society
that is going to be antisocial and the
way that I came to understand this is
that about 1% of any population is born
psychopathic meaning that they're not
able to feel bad about harm caused to
others so they have to learn the rules
of the social group and experience the
social modeling or the social behavior
that they need to learn by how other
people treat them and so what he did as
he looked at a particular time in our
evolutionary history which was the time
when small bands of hunter-gatherer
societies typically of 30 to 50 members
would engage in big game hunting and big
game hunting requires cooperation and
then sharing of the spoils of
so one thing that he found was that in
all hunter-gatherer societies that
anthropologists have studied and he did
a law a very comprehensive and broad
survey of the anthropological research
was he found that in all cases they were
egalitarian and he asked the question
how did this cooperative behavior arise
and the simple answer in case you don't
want to read the book and just cut to
the chase is that he found that for the
antisocial behaviors these people that
would be want to be dictators or bullies
in other words the Psychopaths that the
group would behave as a collective
individual to suppress that bully and
keep them from rising to power so they
did this through three levels of social
sanctioning the first level was shaming
meaning that if a person engaged in
antisocial behavior they were humiliated
in front of the group and if this didn't
work then they went to the next level
which was ostracism kicking that
individual out of the group because they
were deemed to be bad for the group and
of course in hunter-gatherer societies
being ostracized meant nearer certain
death so this was quite a significant
behavior and then the third level of
sanctioning of behavior which happened
much less frequently was execution
meaning that if the individual was bound
to be I'm so harmful to the community
and they weren't able to remove the
their behavior through the earth the
less of your means than in very rare
cases they would actually execute them
so this tells us a very important lesson
that in our world as we move into the
21st century we need to reclaim the
sanctioning of moral behavior meaning we
need to have collective sanctions
against bad behavior if we want to
promote the innate and natural
pro-social and cooperative behaviors of
humans so if you want to understand more
about how this works and what
anthropologists have learned across the
decades of research and how pro-social
behavior arises in human groups and also
how to design social policies that
promote social behavior and deter
antisocial behavior then this is one of
those foundational texts that you will
want to read so again
moral origins by Christopher Boehm an
extremely important piece of scholarly
work that is accessible to the layperson
so there you have it i hope this is
useful for you and if you need to learn
more about this go and grab the book